Guide to the New-York Historical Society Poster Collection [dates] PR 55
New-York Historical Society
New-York Historical Society poster collection
18xx-20xx
New-York Historical Society
PR 55
.01 Linear feet
TBD
Arrangement
TBD
Biographical / Historical
TBD
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
TBD
Scope and Contents
TBD
- Series I. Art Posters, 1890-1910; 612 item(s) (approximately)
  Scope and Contents
  The Art Posters Series consists of approximately 612 striking prints used to advertise magazines, books, and newspapers. Notable artists include Edward Penfied and Joseph J. Gould. A separate inventory for this series is found through this link: Art Posters
- Series II. Circus Posters, 18xx-19xx
  tbd
  Since the folders maybe no longer have a thematic orientation since they were item cataloged, an interesting, though time-consuming, option could be to copy a brief opening description from Bobcat items, then include the link to launch to the full description. One example for the first item in the collection is included. The oversize was not item cataloged, so we would just list the folders from the paper finding aid.
  - The G[rea]test natural curiosity in the known world!... (Folder 02-01, Item 01)
    Link to Bobcat entry for fuller item detail
- Series III. Civil War Posters, 1861-1865; 466 item(s) (approximately)
  The Civil War Posters consist of a total of 466 items. Of this total, 275 are recruiting posters, 31 are posters advertising auctions, drives, meetings, and the remaining 160 items refer to deserter lists, muster rolls, and various other announcements and newspaper clippings pertaining to the Civil War. The recruiting posters represent a variety of Civil War regiments from the states of Maine, Massachusetts, New Jersey, New York, and Pennsylvania in the areas of artillery, cavalry, and infantry. Most of the recruiting posters come from New York followed by New Jersey and Pennsylvania. Also noted on many recruiting posters are the types of men desired. These desired men may have been African Americans, Germans (11 are written in German), Irish, married or single men.
  The iconography of the recruiting posters also makes them quite distinct. Icons, in color and black and white, depict the spreading wings of an eagle with banners, valiant cavalry men on horses, beautiful harps, and the heroic face of George Washington to name only a few. For many posters, it is the icon that is the prominent image on the poster and draws the viewer's attention. Other posters of interest may be found in the 160 items which are not recruiting posters. Some of these items include songs, poems, and even a hospital slipper pattern. The deserter lists in these 160 items demonstrate the indignance of officials against deserters and the posting of rewards to track down such persons.
  There is a separate inventory for the Civil War posters found at this link: Civil War Posters
  [The linked finding aid does not include the 100+ posters other than recruitig so they'll need to be added there, though not at an item level.]
- Series IV. World's Fair and Other Fairs Posters, 1893-1965; .01 item(s)
  [probably does not need item level]
  - Bristol Cattle Show and Fair!, 1854 (Folder FF-1)
    Poster published by Ontario County Times Power Press, Canandaigua, N.Y. The Bristol Agricultural and Mechanic's Association, Royal A. Andrews (President), sponsored the fair and the executive committee was comprised of Royal A. Andrews, William Thomas, W.G. Donielson, A. Jones, B.F. Hicks, and N.W. Randall. On back (in pencil), "November 29. 1951 William".
  - "Diploma" awarded by Fairfield County Agricultural Society, 1856 (Folder FF-1)
    Lith. of Sarony, Major & Knapp. Diploma awarded to Mr. J.M. Rose of Greenwich, Ct., by Tho. B. Butler, President, and A.H. Ryingcord(sp?), Secretary, as a Premium for fine collection of imported and fancy breeds of Fowls. On front(in pencil), "Sept. 27, 1927". On back(in pencil), "Gift of Mr. DeWitt M. Lockman. Sept. 7, 1934".
  - "Triumphs of the Age: Being a Memorial of the Sixteenth Exhibition of the Ohio Mechanic's Institute...", 1858 (Folder FF-1)
    Poster printed by Longley Brothers, Printers. Cincinnati, Ohio. Memorial written by R.E.H. Levering. Acquisition date(?) on front: Oct. 7/99.
  - Third Annual Exhibition and Fair of the Suffield Agricultural Society, 1861 (Folder FF-1)
    Poster published by Samuel Bowles & Company, Printers, Springfield. Officers of the Society were Gad Sheldon, David Rising, Nathan Clark, James B. Rose, H.S. Sheldon, F.P. Loomis, and Francis Sheldon. On back, stamped, "The New-York Historical Society Folk Arts Collection November 17, 1937".
  - East Granville Corners Cattle Show and Fair, 1862 (Folder FF-1)
    The officers of the Show and Fair were as follows: William Moore, President; Samuel T. Ellis, Marshal; Selvin Crosby, Ass't Marshal; J.M. Gibbons, Treasurer; and Ansel Clark, Secretary. Committees included ones for oxen, fancy matched cattle, sheep and swine, poultry, stallions, vegetables, fruits, and grains, fancy articles, and mechanical products. Stamped on back, "The New-York Historical Society Folk Arts Collection November 17, 1937".
  - "Our Daily Fare!" The Great Central Fair Newspaper, 1864 (Folder FF-1)
    Poster was printed by Henry B. Ashmead, Printer. The special subscription newspaper published daily during the continuance of The Great Central Fair held in Philadelphia was published by Geo. W. Childs, Philadelphia. On front (in pencil), "May 15/06".
  - Grand Charitable Fair and Presentation Festival in aid of the Home and School for the Maintenance and Education of the Destitute Children of our Soldiers and Sailors., 1866 (Folder FF-1)
    The Fair was held at the Public Hall, Corner of Broadway and 23rd Street. Presents, including 10,000 in U.S. Greenbacks and a country residence in Westchester, were awarded at the Grand Presentation Festival held at the Cooper Institute. Thomas & Co. were the managing directors. Special notice concerning the prize tickets on the back of poster.
  - 23d Annual Harden County Fair held on the grounds of the Society at Kenton, IA., 1889 (Folder FF-1)
    Poster (Sample Half Sheet No. 27) published by The Fair Publishing House Poster Print, Norwalk, Ohio. M.G. Botsford was president and A.L. Marshal was secretary of the Society.
  - Items from 1893 Chicago Worlds Fair, 1894 (Folder FF-2)
    Most of the items appear to be from an artfolio published by The White City Art Company of Chicago and Denver. The artfolio was issued weekly with four plates (80 in total were intended to be reproduced) and text by Stanley Wood, Esq. It was printed by The Lakeside Press, R.R. Donnelley & Sons, Co., Chicago. The images are as follows:
    Reproductions copyrighted by W.H. Jackson and published by Franklin Co., Chi. 1. Mining and Electricity Buildings, from Transportation Building. 2. Golden Door of Transportation Building. 3. Manufactures Building, from Horticultural Hall. 4. View South East from The Illinois Building. 5. General View, from The Lake. 6. View North, from between Manufactures and Electricity Buildings. 7. Transportation Building, from Wooded Island. 8. The Water Gate. 9. Fire Boat and Agricultural Building. 10. Agricultural Building, from Colonnade. 11. Manufactures Building, from Casino. 12. Columbia Avenue in Manufactures Building. 13. MacMonnies Fountain, from South Terrace. 14. The Woman's Building. 15. Interior of Woman's Building.
    Reproductions copyrighted by W.H. Jackson and published by A. Zeese & Co., Chi. 1. Peristyle and the Water Gate, from Grand Basin. (2 copies) 2. Government Building and Wooded Island. (2 copies) 3. West View of Manufactures Building. 4. Chicago Day. 5. The Administration Building, from the South East. 6. MacMonnies Fountain, from Grand Plaza. (2 copies)
    Reproductions published by Franklin Co., Chi. 1. Main Entrance of Woman's Building. 2. View from Balcony of Woman's Building. 3. Rear View of MacMonnies Fountain. 4. MacMonnies Fountain, from the South 5. Statue of Columbus, East Entrance Administration Building. 6. Statue of Industry. 7. The White City at Midnight. 8. East Façade of Machinery Hall. 9. Manufactures and Electricity Buildings, from Squatter's Hut. 10. Statue of Plenty. 11. South Entrance of Mining Building. 12. German Government Building. 13. The Immense Crowd. 14. Bird's-Eye View of State Buildings at the White City.
    Other reproductions 1. Statue of Cowboy 2. Group of Statuary, Transportation Building 3. Statue of Indian Scout 4. North Façade of Mining Building
    The other items in the folder are: 1. Photograph by C.D. Arnold (official photographer) of Interior of Manufactures and Liberal Arts Building.
    2. 9 illustrations (by E. Eldon Deane, M. Kenyan(?), del., and William LeBaron Jenney, architect, and unsigned) and long captions of The Woman's Building, The Fish and Fisheries Building, The Agricultural Building, The Mines and Mining Building, The Electrical Building, The Horticulural Building, The Transportation Building, The Machinery Hall, and The Administration Building.
    3. Unsigned illustration of Bird's Eye View of the Worlds Columbian Exposition, Showing Designs and Grouping of all Buildings Now Determined Upon.
  - Items from Chicago Worlds Fair, 1894 (Folder FF-3)
    All items are reprouctions that appear to be from an artfolio published by The White City Art Company of Chicago and Denver. The artfolio was issued weekly with four plates (80 in total were intended to be reproduced) and text by Stanley Wood, Esq. It was printed by The Lakeside Press, R.R. Donnelley & Sons, Co., Chicago. The images are as follows:
    Reproductions copyrighted by W.H. Jackson and published by Franklin Co., Chi. 1. Statue of the Republic and Peristyle. 2. The Caravels from the Bridge. 3. View North West, from Manufactures Building. 4. La Rabida, from South West Side. 5. Electricity Building, Looking South West. 6. North Lagoon, from Mining Building. 7. View of North Lagoon, Art Palace and State Buildings. 8. North Front of Agricultural Building. 9. Horticultural Building, from Wooded Island. 10. Administration Building, Looking North East. 11. Looking South between Electricity and Mining Buildings. 12. View South East from The Illinois Building. 13. Peristyle from Lake. 14. Statue of Liberty. 15. View of the Lake Front. 16. General View, from The Lake 17. Lake Front, from Manufactures Building. 18. State Buildings of Massachusetts, New York and Pennsylvania. 19. The Obelisk and Grand Vista North from Colonnade. 20. South Façade of Art Palace. 21. Choral Hall, from Wooded Island. 22. Agricultural Building, from Colonnade. 23. Interior of Choral Hall. 24. Fire Boat and Agricultural Building. 25. Machinery Hall, from Colonnade. 26. Machinery Hall, from North East. 27. Looking North between Mines and Electricity Buildings.
    Reproductions copyrighted by W.H. Jackson and published by A. Zeese & Co., Chi. 1. The Administration Building, from the South East. 2. The Fisheries Building.
    Reproductions published by Franklin Co., Chi. 1. South Colonnade. 2. Interior of Electricity Building. 3. North West Corner Agricultural Building. 4. Main Entrance of Agricultural Building. 5. Ferris Wheel, and Bird's-Eye View of Midway. 6. Court of Honor, Looking West. 7. Court of Honor, Looking East. 8. Panorama of State Buildings, from North East. 9. Details of Main Entrance of Art Palace. 10. Administration Building at Night, from Electricity Building. 11. Electricity Building and Fountain. 12. East Entrance Horticultural Building. 13. Midway Plaisance, Looking West.
    Other reproductions 1. View North from Colonnade. 2. Administration Building, from Agricultural Building. 3. Agricultural Building at Night, from North West.
  - Westchester County Fair Horse and Cattle Show at White Plains, N.Y., 1899 (Folder FF-1)
    Poster published by Hennegan & Co., Cincinnati. James Hopkins, President, and E.B. Long, Secretary, for the Fair committee. The Great Baby show, the Japanese Day Fireworks, and the Parisian Dog Hippodrome were a few of the entertainment acts. On front (in pencil), "E.B. Child Feb. 1946". More information about the fair is published on the reverse side.
  - Your Town That Village of 8,000,000 People, 1938 (Folder FF-4)
    Copyright by Robert K. Straus, Councilman, and drawn by Fred Cooper. Features a pictorial map of New York City advertising the Robert K. Straus' radio show on Monday nights at 8:30 on WHN at 1010 on the dial.
  - The New York Official World's Fair Pictorial Map, 1939 (Folder FF-4)
    Created by Tony Sarg and published by Tony Sarg Publications, Inc., N.Y. Printed in U.S.A. by Pace Press, Inc., N.Y.C. Front cover features Trylon and Perisphere. Map lists alphabetically exhibits and amusement area. On back, places to eat at the Fair. 4 pages.
  - The New York Official World's Fair Pictorial Map, 1939 (Folder FF-4)
    Several page pamphlet created by Tony Sarg and published by Tony Sarg Publications, Inc., N.Y. Printed in U.S.A. by Pace Press, Inc., N.Y.C. Front cover features Trylon and Perisphere. The pamphlet has a large map and several detailed maps of each area of the fairgrounds. Acquisition date(?), in pencil, on back, Oct. 14, 1939.
  - Matted Tony Sarg Pictorial Map of New York World's Fair, 1939 (Folder FF-4)
    Published by Tony Sarg Publications, Inc., New York, N.Y. This pictorial map is unfolded and matted.
  - "Only 2,075 Miles To Go!", 1939 (Folder FF-4)
    Copyright, 1939, National Geographic Society. Printed in U.S.A. Dufaycolor Photograph by Luis Marden. Features a young man, holding a New York sign, hitchhiking on a bridge that includes signage: "2075 miles to George Washington Bridge, Holland Tunnel, Lincoln Tunnel". The caption explains, "These signs on the International Bridge at Laredo, Texas, were provided by the New York World's Fair."
  - Pamphlet on Ford Building at the New York World's Fair (Folder FF-4)
    The front cover features the Ford Building and the Road of Tomorrow. The back cover features five car models produced by Ford. On the inside pages is printed The New Yorker's Map of the World of Tomorrow together with an index to its principal features, revised for issue of July 8, 1939, created by Carl Rose.
  - New York World's Fair certificate of appointment to Advisory Committee on Women's Participation, 1939 (Folder FF-4)
    The certificate features the Trylon and Perisphere and appointed Mrs. Ripley Hitchcock to the committee. It was signed by the President, Grover Whalen, and sceretary.
  - New York World's Fair certificate of appointment to Advisory Committee on Patriotic and Historical Societies, 1939 (Folder FF-4)
    The certificate features the Trylon and Perisphere and appointed Mr. Alexander Wall to the committee. It was signed by the President, Grover Whalen, and sceretary.
  - New York World's Fair Kerchief Designs, c.1939 (Folder FF-5)
    18 Kerchief designs for the World's Fair. NYHS also owns many of the kerchiefs based on these designs.
    1. Scarlett O'Hara. Designed by Eaton and D.W. Serrano Studio Designers, New York. Acquisition date(?) on back, Oct. 7, 1941. 2. Scarlett-Rhett. Designed by Eaton and D.W. Serrano Studio Designers, New York. Acquisition date(?) on back, Oct. 7, 1941. 3. New York World's Fair. (Featuring significant buildings and Trylon and Perisphere). Designed by Eaton and copyrighted by the NYWF. Acquisition date(?) on back, Oct. 7, 1941. 4. New York World's Fair. (Featuring areas of interest and Trylon and Perisphere). Designed by Eaton and Royal Studios and copyrighted by the NYWF. Acquisition date(?) on back, Oct. 7, 1941. 5. World's Fair Music Hall. Designed by Eaton and copyrighted by NYWF. Acquisition date(?) on back, Oct. 7, 1941. 6. Trylon and Perisphere. Designed by Eaton (M. Eaton & Co., New York) and copyrighted by NYWF. Acquisition date(?) on back, Oct. 7, 1941. 7. New York World's Fair Horticultural Exhibit. Designed by Eaton. Acquisition date(?) on back, Oct. 7, 1941. 8. Aviation Building, Health Science Medical and Education Building, Contemporary Art Building, and Maritime Building. Designed by Eaton and copyrighted by NYWF. Acquisition date(?) on back, Oct. 7, 1941. 9. Rockefeller Center New York. Designed by Eaton. Acquisition date(?) on back, Oct. 7, 1941. 10. Boston Monuments. (Including Faneuil Hall, Old State House, Old North Church). Designed by Eaton and D.W. Serrano Studio Designers, New York. Acquisition date(?) on back, Oct. 7, 1941. 11. Little Church around the Corner. Designed by Eaton. Acquisition date(?) on back, Oct. 7, 1941. 12. New York World's Fair 1939: The World of Tomorrow. Designed by Eaton. Acquisition date(?) on back, Oct. 7, 1941. 13. "Americana" Patriotic Design in Red, White, and Blue, with Eagle. Acquisition date (?) on back, Aug. 13, 1941. In pencil, on back, "From Edgar C. Hywanth…" 14. New York City Monuments. (Including Empire State Building, Metropolitan Museum). Designed by Eaton and D.W. Serrano Studio Designers, New York. Acquisition date(?) on back, Oct. 7, 1941. 15. Pictorial Map of Manhattan and How to get to World's Fair. Designed by Eaton and copyrighted by NYWF. Acquisition date(?) on back, Oct. 7, 1941. 16. New York Public Library (2 copies. One colored green and tan, one colored pink, blue, and green) Designed by Eaton. Acquisition date(?) on back, Oct. 7, 1941. 17. Statue of Liberty. Designed by Eaton. Acquisition date(?) on back, Oct. 7, 1941. 18. World's Fair Administration Building. Designed by Eaton and copyrighted by NYWF. Acquisition date(?) on back, Oct. 7, 1941.
  - The World's Fair of 1940 for Peace and Freedom...Opens May 11 (Folder FF-4)
    Poster on illustration board hand done by E.P. Chrystie. Features bird's-eye view of the fairgrounds. Acquisition date(?), in pencil, on back, February 27, 1952.
  - Ford 1940 (Folder FF-4)
    Poster on illustration board hand done by E.P. Chrystie. Features hood of car with Ford logo. Acquisition date(?), in pencil, on back, February 27, 1952.
  - For Peace and Freedom. The World's Fair New York...Opens May 11th, 1940 (Folder FF-4)
    Poster on illustration board hand done by E.P. Chrystie. Features flags of the world. Acquisition date(?), in pencil, on back, February 27, 1952.
  - World's Fair New York 1940 for Peace and Freedom (Folder FF-4)
    Poster on illustration board hand done by E.P. Chrystie. Features Ford Building. Acquisition date(?), in pencil, on back, February 27, 1952.
  - The World's Fair of 1940 New York Opens May 11th (Folder FF-4)
    Poster on illustration board hand done by E.P. Chrystie. Features monumental statue of George Washington. Acquisition date (?), in pencil, on back, February 27, 1952.
  - Visit International Centennial Stamp Exhibition, British Pavilion World's Fair, 1940 (Folder FF-4)
    Poster created by Bob Smith. Features the "Penny Black", the World's first postage stamp issued in 1840.
  - Peace and Freedom. World's Fair of 1940 in New York (Folder FF-4)
    2 copies. Poster was made in U.S.A. by Polygraphic Company of America, Inc. N.Y.C. Poster features Trylon and Perisphere and the Constitution Mall. Acquisition date(?), in pencil, on back of both copies, June 20, 1940.
  - World's Fair of 1940 in New York Announcement of Opening Day (Folder FF-4)
    Poster was made in U.S.A. by Polygraphic Company of America, Inc., N.Y.C. Opening day was May 11th and admission was 50 cents. Poster features flags of the World and a monumental statue. Acquisition date(?), in pencil, on back, April 4, 1940. An attached cover letter from The World's Fair of 1940 in New York asks recepient to hang poster in library in an effort to bring more people to the Fair.
  - World's Fair of 1940 in New York Announcement of Opening Day (Folder FF-4)
    The poster was made in U.S.A. by Polygraphic Company of America, Inc., N.Y.C. and designed by Howard Scott. Features a patriotic older gentleman in hat and three-piece suit at the Fair. Opening day was May 11th and admission was 50 cents. Acquisition date(?), in pencil, on back, April 4, 1940.
  - "Go By All Means World's Fair in New York 1940" (Folder FF-4)
    2 copies. Poster made in U.S.A. by Polygraphic Company of America, Inc., N.Y.C. Poster created by S. Ekman. Acquisition date(?), in pencil, on back of both copies, June 20, 1940.
  - "For Your Summer Vacation...World's Fair New York", 1939 (Folder FF-4)
    2 copies. Poster made in U.S.A. by Polygraphic Company of America, Inc., N.Y.C. Poster designed by Bob Smith with the tagline, "Travel America...See the World at the World's Fair in New York". Acquisition date(?), in pencil, on back of both copies, June 20, 1940.
  - Reproduction: "Country Fair" by John A. Woodside, 1824., 1940 (Folder FF-1)
    Reproduced print is an offset lithography by Rogers-Kellogg-Stillson of the original painting in the collection of Harry T. Peters. It is attached to the front of a greeting card from Harry T. Peters. On the back of the card, Peters explained that "Country Fair", depicting a country fair near the city of Philadelphia, is believed to be the first graphic record in America of a country fair. On back (in pencil), "Dec. 26, 1940".
  - "Perisphere, Melting into History", 1941 (Folder FF-4)
    Photograph and caption from the New York Journal and American, February 27, 1941. Features a dismantled Perisphere with the caption explaining that the salvaged metal would go to the Defense program.
  - Newspaper photograph of the steel skeletons of the Trylon and Perisphere, c. 1941 (Folder FF-4)
    Photograph and caption from a newspaper, undated.
  - Reprint: "Sights at the Fair Ground.", c. 1955 (Folder FF-1)
    Reprint of a 1888 Currier & Ives print. On front(in pencil) "#10472 (c.1955)" Stamped in many places "N.Y. Public Library Picture Collection". On back, a note on the Currier & Ives prints, "The Road ..."
  - "Come back to the Fair" New York's World's Fair, 1961 (Folder FF-6)
    3 copies. "Unisphere presented by United States Steel copyrighted 1961, 1962 New York World's Fair 1964-1965 Corporation" Printed by Allied Printing, Philadelphia. On back of all copies stamped, "This publication was presented to this Library by Peter M. Warner."
  - "New York World's Fair 1964-1965", 1961 (Folder FF-6)
    3 copies. Poster designed by B. Peak. "Unisphere presented by United States Steel copyrighted 1961, 1962 New York World's Fair 1964-1965 Corporation". Printed by Amalgamated Lithographers of America, New York -- "Litho in U.S.A." Stamped on back of all copies, "This publication was presented to this Library by Peter M. Warner".
  - "Come back to the Fair!" New York World's Fair, 1961 (Folder FF-6)
    3 copies. "Unisphere presented by United States Steel copyrighted 1961 New York World's Fair 1964-1965 Corporation" Printed by Allied Printing, Philadelphia. Stamped on back of all copies, "This publication was presented to this Library by Peter M. Warner".
  - "New York World's Fair 1964-1965", 1961 (Folder FF-6)
    6 copies (2 mounted on cardboard with easel backs). Poster designed by B. Peak. "Unisphere presented by United States Steel copyrighted 1961, 1962 New York World's Fair 1964-1965 Corporation". Printed by Amalgamated Lithographers of America, New York -- "Litho in U.S.A." Stamped on back of some copies, "This publication was presented to this Library by Peter M. Warner".
  - "Texas Pavilions. Music Hall.", c.1961 (Folder FF-6)
    Photograph of Texas Pavilions model. Stamped on back, "This publication was presented to this Library by Peter M. Warner".
- Series V. Political Posters, 18xx-20xx; 100 item(s) (approximately)
  [not many. might be worth item level or something a little descriptive]
  - Tippecanoe (Harrison & Tyler) Log Cabin by Whigs of Buffalo, 1840 (Folder FF-1)